<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "REST_API_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-REST_API_Guide-Authentication">
  <title>Authentication</title>

  <para>
    An API user provides a mandatory Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager username and password with all requests to the API and uses HTTP Basic Authentication
    <footnote>
      <para>
        Basic Authentication is described in <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2617">RFC 2617 HTTP Authentication: Basic and Digest Access Authentication</ulink>.
      </para>
    </footnote>
    to encode these credentials. If a request does not include an appropriate <literal>Authorization</literal> header then the API sends a <literal>401 Authorization Required</literal> as a result:
  </para>

  <screen>
HEAD [base] HTTP/1.1
Host: [host]

HTTP/1.1 401 Authorization Required
  </screen>

  <para>
    Request are issued with an <literal>Authorization</literal> header for the specified realm. An API user encodes an appropriate Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager domain and user in the supplied credentials with the <uri>username@domain</uri> convention.
  </para>  
  <example>
    <title>Encoding authentication credentials</title>
    <informaltable frame="none">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="2*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="5*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Item</entry>
            <entry>Value</entry>
          </row>
        </thead> 
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>username</entry>
            <entry>rhevmadmin</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>domain</entry>
            <entry>domain.example.com</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>password</entry>
            <entry>123456</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>unencoded credentials</entry>
            <entry>rhevmadmin@domain.example.com:123456</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>base64 encoded credentials</entry>
            <entry>cmhldm1hZG1pbkBibGFjay5xdW1yYW5ldC5jb206MTIzNDU2</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
      An API user provides the encoded credentials as shown:
    </para>

    <screen>
HEAD [base] HTTP/1.1
Host: [host]
Authorization: Basic cmhldm1hZG1pbkBibGFjay5xdW1yYW5ldC5jb206MTIzNDU2

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
...
    </screen>
  </example>
  <note>
    <title>Confidentiality</title>
    <para>
      Basic authentication involves potentially sensistive information such as passwords being sent in plain text. The REST API requires Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure (HTTPS) for transport-level encryption of requests. The Internet Engineering Task Force provides an RFC explaining HTTPS at <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2818.txt">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2818.txt</ulink>.
    </para>
  </note>
    <note>
    <title>Multiple Lines</title>
    <para>
      Some base64 libraries break the result into multiple lines and terminates each line with a newline character. This breaks the header and causes a faulty request. The Authorization header requires the encoded credentials on a single line within the header.
    </para>
  </note>

</chapter>
