<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "REST_API_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-REST_API_Guide-Cluster_Level_Versions">
  <title>Compatibility Level Versions</title>
  <para>
    Each hosts connected to Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager contains a version of <acronym>VDSM</acronym>. VDSM is the agent within the virtualization infrastructure that runs on a hypervisor or host and provides local management for virtual machines, networks and storage. Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager controls hypervisors and hosts using current or older versions of VDSM.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Manager migrates virtual machines from host to host within a cluster. This means the Manager excludes certain features from a current version of VDSM until all hosts within a cluster have the same VDSM version, or more recent, installed.
  </para>
  <para>
    The API represents this concept as a <literal>compatibility level</literal> for each host, corresponding to the version of VDSM installed. A <literal>version</literal> element contains <literal>major</literal> and <literal>minor</literal> attributes, which describe the compatibility level.
  </para>
  <para>
    When an administrator upgrades all hosts within a cluster to a certain level, the <literal>version</literal> level appears under a <literal>supported_versions</literal> element. This indicates the cluster's <literal>version</literal> is now updatable to that level. Once the administrator updates all clusters within a data center to a given level, the data center is updatable to that level.
  </para>
  <example>
    <title>Upgrading compatibility levels from Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager&nbsp;2.2 to 3.0</title>
    <para>
      The API reports the following compatibility levels for Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization Manager&nbsp;2.2 instance:
    </para>
    <screen>
&lt;host ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/host&gt;

&lt;cluster ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
    </screen>
    <para>
      All hosts within a cluster are updated to VDSM <literal>3.0</literal> and the API reports:
    </para>
    <screen>
&lt;host ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="3" minor="0"/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/host&gt;

&lt;cluster ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions&gt;
        &lt;version major="3" minor="0"/&gt;
    &lt;/supported_versions&gt;
    ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
    </screen>
    <para>
      The cluster is now updatable to <literal>3.0</literal>. When the cluster is updated, the API reports:
    </para>
    <screen>
&lt;cluster ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="3" minor="0"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/cluster&gt;

&lt;data_center ...&gt;
    ...
    &lt;version major="2" minor="2"/&gt;
    &lt;supported_versions&gt;
        &lt;version major="3" minor="0"/&gt;
    &lt;/supported_versions&gt;
    ...
&lt;/data_center&gt;
    </screen>
    <para>
      The API user updates the data center to <literal>3.0</literal>. Once upgraded, the API exposes features available in Red Hat Enterprise Virtualization&nbsp;3.0 for this data center.
    </para>
  </example>
</chapter>
